Replacing the authorization servlet

It is also possible to replace the authorization servlet in any version of OA4MP with a customized version. You may then, for instance, use LDAP or Shibboleth for authentication. The protocols require that your module occupy the authorize endpoint. The assumptions then are that

Your module will handle the authentication.
After a successful authentication, your module will make a callout to another, private endpoint.
This private endpoint is tasked to set up all the state and check that the request is valid. Skipping a call to this module means there will be no state for this request and all subsequent attempts to use the service will be rejected.
This private endpoint is either protected at the network level (access via Apache) or with a security constraint in Tomcat (Tomcat only servers).
Your call to this will follow a mini-protocol, then process the response. Each version of OA4MP has its own details on this.

Having Tomcat handle security.

If you have a Tomcat only service, then you must protect this endpoint. A typical security security constraint is the following, which should be added to the deployment descriptor (web.xml file)

    <security-constraint>
           <web-resource-collection>
               <web-resource-name>Lockdown_initiate_endpoint</web-resource-name>
               <url-pattern>/authorized</url-pattern>
               <http-method>GET</http-method>
               <http-method>POST</http-method>
               <http-method>PUT</http-method>
               <http-method>DELETE</http-method>
           </web-resource-collection>
           <auth-constraint/>
       </security-constraint>

which will prevent all access to the authorized endpoint except from Tomcat itself. If you access the service from Apache, you will have to limit access to this endpoint at the server level to calls from localhost only. The authorized servlet comes with this security constraint enabled by default since it is better to have the authentication fail if there is any question about the setup.

Accessing the Authorized Servlet for OA4MP

Initial setup

The servlet used in this case is named OA2AuthorizedServlet. So a typical entry would look like

  <servlet>
      <servlet-name>authorized</servlet-name>
      <servlet-class>org.oa4mp.server.proxy.OA2AuthorizationServer</servlet-class>
  </servlet>
  <servlet-mapping>
      <servlet-name>authorized</servlet-name>
      <url-pattern>/authorized</url-pattern>
  </servlet-mapping>

Note that the name of this servlet may be altered without changing the protocol. Some installation prefer to call it /init since authorize and authorized are very similar.

The mini-protocol

The very first step in the OAuth 2.0 protocol is that the user goes to the authorize endpoint which will then simply call the end authorized endpoint by passing along verbatim the original request your authorization module received. For instance, if your server got the following request

https://your.server.edu/oauth2/authorize?state=s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy&nonce=ABC75344A&...

You do the authorization and once completed successfully, you call the authorized servlet:

https://localhost/oauth2/authorized?state=s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy&nonce=ABC75344A&...

All state and error checking will be done for you. You will simply receive the standard response (with HTML status code of 200, since 302 is reserved for error conditions -- see below for more) in JSON of the token and the state (if that was passed in the initial request) -- simply pass this response back to the client in the standard OIDC redirect. For instance

    {"code":"urn:oauth2:aMQ53UmEtb5cM6WF/ps7wOmYQoJTTKAW9","state":"s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy"}

Errors

The authorized servlet supports all of the same error codes as the standard OAuth 2.0/OIDC specification. This means that there will be an HTML status code of 302 (a redirect) to the callback url that the client supplied (in the request and at registration). This may again be passed along directly to the client which is required to process it. For example, if the above request were invalid and had consequently, failed then if the base url of the error is https://your.client.org/cb your authorize module would get the following redirect, as per the OA4MP/OIDC spec:

    Location: https://your.client.org/cb?
      error=invalid_request
      &error_description=
        the%20request%20is%20not%20valid%20or%20malformed
      &state=s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy

Clients and Prototypes

Clients have the ability to take the non-trivial settings from other clients, called prototypes. Non-trivial settings are those that are greater than equal to zero (if a number, like a token lifetime), non-empty if a string or date. The names of clients are never overwritten. The list of prototypes are processed in order, the values of each override the previous. The current client is the final one processed, then the resulting client is used.

Using the client management API

You may set prototypes as a list of identifiers in the client management API. This is the content of the sample prototype-minimal.json configuration bundled with the oidc-cm toolkit

    {
       "comment":["This is a the minimal request object required for creation: a set of URIs and a name",
         "This also sets prototypes, so that all the settings will be taken from them."
         ],
       "redirect_uris":["https://client.example.org/callback"],
       "client_name": "My Example",
       "prototypes": ["client:/ldap_0", "client:/ligo/onboarding"]
      }

Here a very minimal client (callback, name) is specified and there are two prototypes. All of the settings from these are taken so that in effect, this client is merely an extension of these.

Prototypes do not need to be approved. As a matter of fact, there is a good argument for not approving them if they simply are used by other clients. A final aside is that while this allows for multiple inheritance, the progression is linear and hence the order you specify the clients determines which has priority: Each overrides the one before. This effectively sidesteps certain potential issues with inheritance, such as the Diamond Problem.

Ersatz clients and inheritance

If a client is an ersatz client (so it has a provisioner or possibly many) a common situation is that the client should really just inherit everything from the provisioner. In that case, the extendsProvisioners attribute of the client is set to true and any provisioners will be treated as prototypes.

Introduction

The intent with demo mode is to set up OA4MP with a minimal but usable system for evaluation. This is done by setting the service tag attribute of demoModeEnabled to true. You will need to make sure that Tomcat is set up correctly for this.

What does this do?

Normally OA4MP needs to have some authorization mechanism, such as replacing the authorize endpoint completely (e.g. CILogon) or perhaps enabling Tomcat's native logins to operate. Many organizations as of this writing have been using X509 certificates for years and are interesting in migrating to JWT signed tokens, which OA4MP handles with aplomb. But this is potentially a very large structural change to an organization and needs to be evaluated and tested.

The problem for a quick demo then is finding all the users (and there may be many, many in an organization) that want to test this. Signing them up may be a daunting task. Enabling demo mode, however, allows an admin to set policies for the tokens and lets users use both authorization code flow and device code flow. The user will be prompted for user name and password, but the password is ignored and the entire purpose of the username is to set the subject for any tokens issued.

The effect of configuring this (as per below) will be that the standard authorization code flow works as expected, and the device code flow will too except that the user must go to the webpage and type in the user code (rather than use the link that has it embedded.)

Again it should be stressed that this demo mode is not for production, but mostly to let administrators easily set up a system and have many testers use the system to see how information flows in it. For production, options are then to either enable Tomcat's authorization or simply replace OA4MP's entire authorization module either with your own or with the CILogon proxy.

Tomcat configuration

Tomcat is configured as if this were a standalone OA4MP install but without configuring the remote user machinery. You need to comment out any password protection for the web pages and instead simply require transport of SSL as follows

    <security-constraint>
        <web-resource-collection>
            <web-resource-name>portalSecurity</web-resource-name>
            <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern>
            <http-method>GET</http-method>
            <http-method>POST</http-method>
        </web-resource-collection>
        <user-data-constraint>
            <transport-guarantee>CONFIDENTIAL</transport-guarantee>
        </user-data-constraint>
    </security-constraint>

Server configuration

The demoModeEnabled attribute in the server tag must be set to true.

The Discovery Service

OA4MP (for OIDC) supports the .well-known endpoint, as per RFC 5785 OAuth 2 Discovery, and OIDC discovery. It should be noted that each instance of OA4MP will have its own location for this which corresponds to that instance. This allows for multiple services in a single domain.

You may also use the discovery service to get the public signing keys. This is at the certs endpoint.

By the specification

According to the specifications (RFC 8414, RFC 5785) a request to the service at the .well-known end point must return the information for the OAuth server. This means that

If Apache webserver is fronting Tomcat, you must use mod_rewrite to forward any requests to the OA4MP Discovery servlet
In a Tomcat only install, you should install the RFC8414 servlet that will automatically forward the requests.

It is also possible to just use the rewrite valve in Tomcat to forward requests, however, since it is possible to have multiple OA4MP instances each with its own Discovery service, the RFC8414 servlet is much more flexible.

A note on issuers.

OA4MP allows for multiple issuers with their own keys and hence discovery pages to be created. The normal way this works is that a virtual organization is created and

Example accessing the well-known page

In this case, Tomcat has been configured to return the well-known page for a single OA4MP install using the RFC8414 webapp. A request to https://services.bigstate.edu/.well-known/openid-configuration will be forwarded to the OA4MP instance and serviced there. See the next example for a typical response.

Example accessing the OA4MP Discovery service directly

If OA4MP is hosted at https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2, then the discovery service is at https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/.well-known/openid-configuration and will return a JSON object such as

    {
     "authorization_endpoint": "https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/authorize",
     "registration_endpoint": "https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/register",
     "token_endpoint": "https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/token",
     "userinfo_endpoint": "https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/userinfo",
     "issuer": "https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2",
     "token_endpoint_auth_methods_supported": ["client_secret_post"],
     "subject_types_supported": ["public"],
     "scopes_supported":  [
      "email",
      "edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.getcert",
      "openid",
      "profile",
      "org.cilogon.userinfo"
     ],
     "response_types_supported":  [
      "code",
      "token",
      "id_token"
     ],
     "claims_supported":  [
      "sub",
      "aud",
      "iss",
      "exp",
      "iat",
      "email"
     ],
     "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported":  [
      "RS256",
      "RS512"
     ],
     "jwks_uri": "https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/certs"
    }

Clients will parse this and use bits of the information (such as which signing algorithms are supported and the location of the public keys). There may be some variation, of course, depending on the server's exact configuration.

Getting the signing keys

This would live at jwks_uri address from the discovery service, so you can go to https://services.bigstate.edu/oauth2/certs from the above example and this will return a JSON WebKey object:

 {"keys": [
   {
   "n": "4x7MbZyiKgD5xnEUOlPugxlUzLdNhbCXJqvrgRNj8w-O2hoHbnbJoA8rppco86LZ1W7WIIeOixw2YncKu5kISxq7lzMa_RNYOghkbeJzhs1PB_rUVkuZyySuLK9I2Q_2nfzlggVgn32JXiGR-u3ZqClGODJ8nh5m-H3eGR7-es2A3abQ4BydXbnAbFTTXMMk0C2w1eM5wgp15ZifdP6zfWkwsTpBYU80dRU1NpyZ2hryBtj6CS2sRKY9U09v-B0WlUL6m9RTDlxeQLwoz89XCe02zAftkTcAEQP56zs8SpUYQX_rVNtdI5KyMiOG8qbuYSt17GYynUB18zgc7sTzQ",
   "e": "AQAB",
   "alg": "RS512",
   "kid": "asdwer34df",
   "use": "sig",
   "kty": "RSA"
  },
   {
   "n": "JFsi9rKTZXkiuXBBX2xt4KQx6AgtjzwUkGHNWFEFIpTs2UiRhtTVLNDAU1ocP512uFPb6iQMe6sIdzxntF_bbstHWEtxLsJmqEgObcniI3jcSDtlnxSNuZUUCtNg1jvxxDSOx4yGtTJgQ8JIqhzrDErCG7rqi-gth2oMLtGHtJji9urMuUch42iRI-YoQ7FkFxGlHYZM23U00h0WKilXB5n-zXgoNZC_ALzhKG5dpZh8BsVC_yTrYAP1cCx8kmie8p7Z9V1U42yHiPxSNkIPuLlpXr4xmWLyD7jVm7ppQVQjWjxNlSBrAzjpYF7BMxWd0k8oJnou_1Pa9uK9z396BQ",
   "e": "AQAB",
   "alg": "RS256",
   "kid": "9k0HPG3moXENne",
   "use": "sig",
   "kty": "RSA"
  }
 ]}

What is it?

One request is to allow for a single QDL script to be used in place of all token configurations.

How's it work?

Rather than have the cfg attribute of a client configuration be something like this (in HOCON/JSON):

    tokens{
     identity{
        type=identity
        qdl{
            load="bgsu/idtoken.qdl"
            xmd={exec_phase="post_token"}
          }// end qdl
        } //end identity token
        access{
           type=wlcg
           issuer="https:cilogon.org"
           audience="https://bgsu.edu/jwt/v1/any"
           lifetime=3600000
           qdl{
              load="bgsu/at.qdl"
              xmd={exec_phase=["post_token","post_refresh","post_exchange"]}
              args=["USER_ID", "PASSWORD"]
           } //end QDL
        } // end access token
       refresh{
         issuer="https:cilogon.org"
         audience="https://bgsu.edu/jwt/v1/any"
         lifetime=3600000000
          qdl{
             load="bgsu/rt.qdl"
             xmd={exec_phase=["post_token","post_refresh","post_exchange"]}
          } //end QDL
      }// end refresh
    } //end tokens

You could have a driver script that is loaded for all phases and allow the script to dispatch the execution. The plus with this is, obviously, you manage the script and once set the client configuration never need be touched. The most important point is that the client cfg then is a single QDL invocation element:

    qdl{
        load="bgsu/driver.qdl"
        xmd={exec_phase="post_all"}
      }// end qdl

In this case, the driver script might start like

    if[
      exec_phase=='post_auth'
    ][
      script_load('bgsu/idtoken.qdl');
    ];
    if[
      exec_phase == 'post_token'
    ][
    // ... etc.
    ];

What this does under the hood is create a handler (id token, access and refresh with gerenic defaults) and sets the script to the single driver.

Caveats

Each invocation of QDL requires marshalling resource, starting an interpreter etc., so while you may certainly request that the exec_phase be "all", there is apt to be an awful lot of extra work done

In the driver, load scripts do not run them, since the ambient scope contains all access tokens, claims etc. and script_run creates a new clean scope with none of that.

Ersatz Clients

Introduction

The ability for a client to take over the flow that another has initiated is referred to as substitution and clients that are specifically tasked with this as referred to as ersatz clients. We use the cognated word 𝕰𝖗s𝖆𝖙𝖟 (which just means substitute in German) because words like delegate, impersonate, substitute etc. are so overloaded in English that discourse is getting hard -- more time is spent on what the word means in context than anything else. An ersatz client has a very specific, narrow definition and there should be few if any conflicts with other nomenclature.

Definition of an ersatz client

An ersatz client in OA4MP is a specific type of client which may substitute for another in a flow. A client that starts a flow is called the provisioning client. A provisioning client is just a standard client in OA4MP and may be confidential or public.

Definition:If A is the provisioning client and α is an ersatz client we say write A ≻ α read A provisions α or α can substitute for A. When A provisions α, we say the flow has forked to α.

Forking a flow

Prerequisites

The provisioning client, A, must exist. The ersatz client α must exist. A must be set as the provisioner of α. This is normally done by an administrator. The steps then are

Start the flow with A. Get access and refresh tokens for A.
Start an exchange using the credentials of α and a valid refresh or access token from A. The requested token type is either omitted or for an access token.
You will receive a response that includes an access token, refresh token and (if applicable) an id token
At this point, the flow has been forked and you simply use the returned tokens with the credentials for α.

Additional notes:

Remember that ersatz clients cannot start flows, they may only substitute for a provisioning client.
The scopes for α are restricted to be at most what A was granted. During the fork, you may downscope. At that point, the resulting scopes become the maximum for α.
If you do the fork and request a refresh token as the return type, you will get exactly a refresh token but can just do a regular exchange or refresh to get access tokens as needed. This can be useful if the ersatz client may have a long wait before actually needing an access token.
You may fork as freely as you like. Every exchange as per above will fork the flow.
OA4MP supports JWTs for authorization which means that A may start a completely automated flow and hand off its work to ersatz clients -- no human intervention is needed. Do read about service clients (OA4MP's name for a client that has sent a public key and can use a JWT).

A not uncommon use is to provision all the permissions for a job with A, then have specific forks for specific permissions (say a fork for read, one for writes, one for managing capabilities, such as starting or stopping jobs.) You could even have dedicated ersatz clients α, β,...

The rest of this document is for more detail or very specialized uses.

Ersatz Client Properties

All ersatz relations are explicit and must be set out of band. This may be done with via the client management endpoint too.
Ersatz clients cannot start a flow.
Ersatz clients can only be substituted at the token exchange (RFC 8693) endpoint.
Once provisioned, they are simply clients can be used at the refresh endpoint, revoked, introspected etc.
Ersatz clients are restricted in their scopes to whatever the provisioning client has and may only downscope.
If A ≻ α, then α inherits the configuration (lifetimes, scripts etc.) from A unless explicitly overridden.
Provisioning chains may have multiple elements: A ≻ α ≻ β ≻ γ ... which connotes an inheritance chain for abilities, not necessarily a custodial chain. Note especially that α, β and γ are ersatz client. There is exactly one provisioning client as the first element of the chain.
≻ is not an ordering relationship! It is perfectly acceptable to have provision multiple clients, A, B, C and set A ≻ α, B ≻ α, C ≻ α. This is because these relations are set by security policies which may be quite arbitrary.
It is perfectly acceptable to have multiple ersatz clients, so A ≻ α, A ≻ β, A ≻ γ.

The token exchange specification has a section on impersonation and delegation semantics. It states in toto

When principal A impersonates principal B, A is given all the rights that B has within some defined rights context and is indistinguishable from B in that context. Thus, when principal A impersonates principal B, then insofar as any entity receiving such a token is concerned, they are actually dealing with B. It is true that some members of the identity system might have awareness that impersonation is going on, but it is not a requirement. For all intents and purposes, when A is impersonating B, A is B within the context of the rights authorized by the token. A's ability to impersonate B could be limited in scope or time, or even with a one- time-use restriction, whether via the contents of the token or an out-of-band mechanism.

What this means is that our substitutions are a form of impersonation and that the trust relations are made out of band. Why not call this impersonation? Because other OAuth systems are free to implement this any way they want, and we want to be clear exactly how we do it. Sad differently, there can be many implmenetations of impersonation with their own policies. We want a unique name so there is no confusion what OA4MP does.

Note on provisioning chains

You may have ersatz clients substitute for other ersatz clients, so A ≻ α, α ≻ β and β ≻ γ is perfectly fine. This means that A provisions α, and that α may substitute for it. Later, β may substitute for α, but cannot substitute for A. This allows for chains of substitution. We may write this chain more compactly as A ≻ α ≻ β ≻ γ.

Creation of Ersatz Clients via the Client Management API

Ersatz clients may be created by an admin client, just like any other. Set the property ersatz_client to true and then set the provisioners. In order to set up the provisioners, you set the property org.oa4mp:/ersatz/provisioners to be either the provisioner ID (i.e., the client ID of the client that an start the flow) or an array of IDs. The zeroth element is always the main provisioner. The list of IDs is

provisionerID ≻ ersatzID_0 ≻ ersatzID_1 ≻ ... ≻ ersatzID_n

All of these must be administered by the same admin client and provision each other in sequence.

If you want the ersatz client to inherit the user metadata (i.e., the id token) then you should set ersatz_inherit_id_token to true. The default is true.

Inheritance etc. (advanced)

Normally if A ≻ α, then A starts the flow and in the token exchange, α presents the access or refresh token to the exchange endpoint. If α is presented for the first time, the flow forks. Note that A cannot resume the flow for α after this point and they become independent, meaning that if A provisions α with an access token, τ, then α exchanges it for τ', A cannot use τ'. On the other hand, if A ≻ β as well then A may provision β with τ too.

Why would you want intermediate ersatz clients?

If you have a very large and complex set of substitutions, you may streamline the flow. Let us say that you have provisioning clients A, B, C, D and you need to have finer grained control. An ersatz client ξ with a specific script (say allowing Lab X) could be used as A ≻ ξ ≻ α and B ≻ ξ ≻ β, (say α and β are used by specific groups within Lab X) so that α and β have consistent behavior but can add their own logic.

Inheritance from provisioners

Clients in OA4MP may set prototypes which are other clients from which they inherit configuration. There may be multiple prototypes (effectively yielding multiple inheritance). Note well that the order you set determines resolution. So if you have 2 prototype clients A and B (in that order) that means that the values of B override the values in A. The values of the base client override all others. This means that you can have a client that is little more than an id and secret which inherits everything else from its prototype, or just sets a single attribute even.

Since provisioning clients can form a prototype hierarchy, there is an attribute for clients namedextendsProvisioners and this means that the provisioners should be used as the prototype hierarchy. If you set this and specify prototypes, then provisioning clients are used first, followed by all specifically set prototypes.

OA4MP extended attributes

These are namespace-qualified parameters that may be sent in any leg of the OAuth flow. They are of the form

    org.oa4mp:X=Y

Where x is a name or a path and Y is the intended value. You may send multiple values. Note the policy for sending these: They simply replace what is there or add it if nothing was there. It is therefore best to send them in the initial request and be done with it.

What do they do?

They allow for a namespace-qualified way to send specific parameters to an OA4MP server's policy engine (i.e., QDL). Now, none of them are directly used by OA4MP, so if your scripts do not use them, they are ignored. They are made available to QDL in the xas. stem.

Clients need to have support enabled

Clients need to have support for extended attributes enabled, either in the CLI using the ea_support command or when registering the client dynamically, sending the boolean-valued ea_support parameter. See dynamic client registration for more details. Failing to do so will simply have them stripped from the request and ignored.

There is a sample QDL script that simply processed certain ones and echos the values in tokens. See process-xas.qdl.

Example

Let us say you made the following request to the authorization end point:

    https://phys.bigstate.edu/oauth2/authorize?org.oa4mp:/tokens/access/lifetime=1000000&org.oa4mp:/roles=admin,all-user&scope=openid... (truncated)

This means that in the QDL environment you would have an xas. (extended attributes) stem of

    {org.oa4mp:{/tokens/access/lifetime:1000000},{/roles:admin,all-use}}

available for use with your policy.

Example of multiple values

If your request had the following values in it

    https://phys.bigstate.edu/oauth2/authorize?&org.oa4mp:/roles=admin&org.oa4mp:/roles=all-user&org.oa4mp:/roles=jira-user&... (truncated)

You would then get an xas. stem with

    {org.oa4mp:   {
        /roles:[admin,all-user,jira-user]
        }
    }

I.e. unlike the first example where the roles are treated as a single string, in the second they are treated as individual entries.

Overview

Welcome to OA4MP server! OA4MP stands for Open Authorization for Many People, and allows open authorization with multiple identities. The server allows for authorization and issues tokens, (hence some call it an issuer). There is also an OA4MP client. Current release is 6.0.

Prerequisites

Tomcat 9 or above. This will not work with Tomcat 8 or lower because of internal changes to Java.
SSL should be configured and enabled. Either in Apache (if you are deploying Tomcat as pass through) or in Tomcat directly. Note that if you do enable SSL in tomcat, you must un-comment the security constraint block in the web.xml deployment descriptor after you deploy the war.
Java 1.11. Higher versions of Java (like Java 17) won't work.
Some form of persistent storage. This may be a file system, Derby, MySQL or PostgreSQL.
Java mail. This must be configured regardless if notifications are set. Read here for details.
Possibly either the latest of

MySQL
Maria DB
PostgreSQL
Apache Derby

OA4MP used to bundle the connectors for these in the wars, but since their licences conflicted with those of some of our users, we decided to simply let you supply them. If you are just using only file-based storage, then you don't need either of these.
Possibly JGlobus. If your server needs to issue limited proxies drop the most recent version of JGlobus jsse (at least 2.0.6) into $CATALINA_HOME/lib as well as, apparently JGlobus-Core (latest release seems to be 2.0.4) and the Bouncy Castle version that support these. Otherwise, you may omit this. Again, be sure you check for the version of Bouncy Castle that your version of JGlobus uses and use that as well. JGlobus-Core 2.0.4 includes Bouncy Castle classes.

Getting and deploying from the war.

This is available as an installer. Download server-installer.jar from the website. This will download and install a full distribution for the version you want. A full set of help is built in to the installer and if you issue

    java -jar server-installer.jar

(so no arguments) it will print out a general help page with instructions. Generally you want to set an environment variable, OA4MP_SERVER and install to that. If you are installing the OA4MP client as well, these should go into different directories. The suggested directory for the server is /opt/oa4mp_server. This jar will install the CLI, download the current war and so forth. It will also create a barebones configuration for you server, in $OA4MP_SERVER/etc. After the installation has finished, follow the instructions. You should set up any databases (see comments in the configuration file and below for databases). A good post install test is to see if the CLI comes up:

my-pc:$OA4MP_SERVER/bin/cli

  .g8""8q.    db                 `7MMM.     ,MMF'`7MM"""Mq.
.dP'    `YM.   ;MM:                  MMMb    dPMM    MM   `MM.
dM'      `MM  ,V^MM.         ,AM     M YM   ,M MM    MM   ,M9
MM        MM ,M  `MM        AVMM     M  Mb  M' MM    MMmmdM9
MM.      ,MP AbmmmqMA     ,W' MM     M  YM.P'  MM    MM
`Mb.    ,dP'A'     VML  ,W'   MM     M  `YM'   MM    MM
  `"bmmd"'.AMA.   .AMMA.AmmmmmMMmm .JML. `'  .JMML..JMML.
                              MM
                              MM
*************************************************************
* OA4MP CLI (Command Line Interpreter)                      *
* Version 6.0                                               *
* By Jeff Gaynor  NCSA                                      *
* type 'help' for a list of commands                        *
*      'exit', 'quit' or '/q' to end this session.          *
*************************************************************
oa4mp>

You may now profitably read how to configure the deployment, and deploy it to Tomcat. The basic configuration for the CLI as delivered should work for the server, although there are many ways to extend and configure OA4MP, so read the comments in the configuration file (has suggestions based on your installation choices) and the documentation.

Deploying to Apache

If you need to deploy this to Apache, one possible way is to use the venerable Proxy AJP connector, proxy_ajp.conf file (which, e.g., lives under /etc/httpd/conf.d in most unix distributions):

ProxyPass /oauth/initiate ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/initiate
ProxyPass /oauth/authorize ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/authorize
... every endpoint you need to support

These entries allow access to all parts of the process. Note: in the WEB-INF/web.xml file there is a section called security-constraint, which controls access to the webapp using Tomcat's SSL. This will conflict with access via Apache, so comment that section out if you are deploying to Apache. It is only needed in stand-alone Tomcat deployments.

Setting up persistent storage

Location of database scripts

In a standard OA4MP install, the scripts to create the databases are all in

$OA4MP_SERVER/etc

These should be run before trying tos tart either the CLI or the server.

File-based storage

(Deprecated) You may store all information for the service in your local file system. It is important that you restrict access to it and back it up. Specifying the storage location in your configuration file is sufficient, since the system will detect if it exists and create anything it needs. See file storage. The advantage is that this is quick to set up and requires no special configuration. The downside is that it does not scale well. If your needs are small, this is fine. If you want a slightly more complex solution that is local (and you don'ave have to manage), use the Derby file store.

MySQL

In order to use MySQL for persistent storage, you must run the supplied script, oa4mp-mysql.sql to create all of the tables and users before your first use:

mysql -u username -p < $OA4MP_SERVER/etc/oa4mp-mysql.sql

(the username is an account (root, e.g.) which has sufficient privileges to create other users) which will prompt you for your password and run the file. See the MySQL configuration for more. If you do not accept the default account names, you must edit this file and replace all occurrences of them manually, as well as setting the passwords. This has to be done because of MySQL's very lousy support for variables. (Should you have to re-run the script, you should manually remove the users and database beforehand. These commands are commented out at the beginning of the file.)

Maria DB

In order to use Maria DB for persistent storage, you must run the supplied script, oa4mp-mariadb.sql to create all of the tables and users before your first use:

mysql -u username -p < $OA4MP_SERVER/etc/oa4mp-mariadb.sql

(the username is an account (root, e.g.) which has sufficient privileges to create other users) which will prompt you for your password and run the file. See the Maria DB configuration for more. If you do not accept the default account names, you must edit this file and replace all occurrences of them manually, as well as setting the passwords. (Should you have to re-run the script, you should manually remove the users and database beforehand. These commands are commented out at the beginning of the file.)

PostgreSQL

Most Unix distros have this database installed by default. There is a specific script, oa4mp-pg.sql, that will create all the tables. All you should need to do is set the passwords near the top of the file. Then you would need to log in to the command line psql tool as the user postgres (this is the super user) and from that prompt issue (replace $OA4MP_SERVER first since psql has no knowledge of environment variables)

\i $OA4MP_SERVER/etc/oa4mp-pg.sql

The file contains default user, table, database and schema names, which you may change if you see fit (be sure to pass these along in your configuration file!). See the Postgres configuration. Again, you only need to edit the values at the top of the file, thanks to PostgreSQL's support for variables.

Apache Derby

There is a specific script, oa4mp-derby.sql, that will create all the tables, however, there is a detailed readme with the particulars in.

$OA4MP_SERVER/derby-setup.txt

All you should need to do is set the passwords near the top of the file. Then you would need to log in to the command line psql tool as the user postgres (this is the super user) and from that prompt issue (replace $OA4MP_SERVER first since psql has no knowledge of environment variables)

\i $OA4MP_SERVER/etc/oa4mp-pg.sql

The file contains default user, table, database and schema names, which you may change if you see fit (be sure to pass these along in your configuration file!). See the Derby configuration. Note that Derby may be used as either a server or locally as a file store. The advantageof the latter is that Derby is bundled with OA4MP and a standard install will create and manage a Derby file store instance for you, making it seamless.

A monitor is simply a client which executes the initial call to an OA4MP server. This works solely from the command line -- no web server is needed. This is exactly the analog of the ping command in that it shows the server up and active. Since a full test of the lifecycle requires that the client be able to accept callbacks i.e. be running a web server, it is not possible to test more than the first call. The intent of the monitor is not to show that everything about configuring a client still works.

To get a functional monitor, you would get oa2-monitor.jar with the script at oa2-monitor The default setup is like any other command line tool with an identical directory layout and it will try to use the configuration found in the default location of /opt/oa4mp/etc/admin-cfg.xml.

Steps to set up a monitor are

Register it with a server
OAuth 2.0 based servers.
Write a configuration file. This should have mail configured.

A quick comment about the callback: The callback supplied must match one of the ones given at registration time or the initial request will be rejected. The comparison is done as strings as per the specification, so logically equivalent callbacks (such as having parameters switched) will fail. 3. Run it once from the command line to see if it works by using the oa4mp-monitor script.

4. Setup a chron job or use monit or whatever tool you prefer to invoke oa4mp-server at some specific interval, e.g. every 5 minutes. The monitor will send an email notification whenever an attempt to contact the server fails.

Last accessed time monitoring.

Various stored objects in OA4MP such as clients, admin clients, ersatz clients and virtual organizations will have their access times logged and updated. Given the nature of the server, this is done by keeping a running log of these accesses and periodically doing a batch update on persistent storage. This keeps the server load to a minimum, since a typical use pattern is that a client is accessed very often at the beginning of a flow then may go a very long time (say awaiting an exchange) before being accessed again. Caching all of the intial accesses into a single call is a much less impactful way of doign it.

How does it work?

The server tag contains three attributes, enableMonitor, monitorInterval and monitorAlarms that control the behavior. You must enable this component to use it, then either set an interval so that the monitor wakes up every interval and runs, or you set specific alarms to run. Alarms are given preferences, so if you set both, you will get alarms. A plus with alarms is that you can schedule them to run when you know server load is low.

How to use this information

You may look at the last accessed time for the object in the CLI. If it has been accessed, then it will have the property last_accessed. You can use this to schedule unsed client cleanups with various parameters for standard clients. This unused client cleanup is also available in the CLI,

What is a service client?

A service client is a specialized OA4MP client that complies with section 2.1 of RFC7523. This means that it is allowed to directly issue a token request without authentication. However, this implies a trust relationship and requires vetting.

Why?

As computing switches to token-based trust models and leaves behind X.509 certificates, services still need to be able to identify themselves and there need to be trust relationships in effect. Before, a server would have an X.509 certificate to prove who or what it was and now it needs a signed token. Requiring a service (and its human administrator) to go through an OAuth flow every time, say, a server restarts, is an intolerable burden on a system. Therefore, the trust is agreed upon separately with a service client. Typically, a service client has a single user and restricts which users can be recognized. Public/private keys must be generated and all authentication is key-based. Once all is in place, the service simply issues a grant request (which is in JSON and also signed with the private key) to the token endpoint, signed with its keys, and gets tokens back.

Authentication generally

As per the spec., section 2.2, a service client must use client authentication. This is in addition to it signing its grant request.

The JSON request

This request replaces the authorization grant request from OAuth. Section 2.1 of RFC7523 lists the requirements. Note that the subject is effectively the username. The list of allowed users may be restricted by setting it in the server's client configuration. In addition, you may include the following parameters:

Attribute | Required? | Default | Description
at_lifetime | N | -- | Request time for the access token to be valid. Note this is subject to server restrictions. See note below about times.
audience | N | -- | A single string or multiple values. These are compliant with RFC 8693 (token exchange).
extended attributes | N | -- | Any OA4MP extended attributes.
resource | N | -- | A single URI or multiple values. These are compliant with RFC 8693 (token exchange).
rt_lifetime | N | -- | Request time for the refresh token to be valid. Note this is subject to server restrictions. See note below about times.
scope | N | -- | A single scope or array of scopes.

About times

Note that the assumption is that all of these without units are in seconds. Blanks before and after units are allowed. Acceptable units are

"ms.", "ms" for milliseconds, e.g. "1000 ms."
"sec.", "sec", "s.", "s" for seconds, e.g., "300 sec"
"min.", "min", "mins.", "mins" for minutes, e.g. "20 min."
"hr.", "hr", "hrs.", "hrs" for hours, "e.g. 2 hrs."
"day", "days" for days, e.g. "1 day", "10 days"

Example

A typical JSON request would be

    {
      "iss": "ashigaru:command.line2",
      "sub": "jeff",
      "jti": "ashigaru:command.line2:/rfc7523/GmGUmD4J0JZH1oAkqNgkeTpWpqklq2HCJi38SuUNV-U",
      "exp": 1686595091,
      "iat": 1686594191,
      "scope":   [
        "org.cilogon.userinfo",
        "openid",
        "profile",
        "email"
      ],
      "oa4mp:/roles": "admin,all-user",
      "oa4mp:/tokens/access/lifetime": 1000000,
      "redirect_uri": "https://oauth.bigstate.edu/client2/ready",
      "nonce": "1yv5JQ5sElsxDHTcObWhJGBp6uy0i4VwMgV4vCHou1I"
    }

Note that this would be turned into the payload of a JWT and signed with the client's private key before being sent to the server.

What is a service client?

A service client is a specialized OA4MP client that complies with either ยง 2.1 of RFC 7523 or with ยง4.4 of the OAuth specification. This means that it is allowed to directly issue a token request without authentication. However, this implies a trust relationship and requires vetting.

Why?

As computing switches to token-based trust models and leaves behind X.509 certificates, services still need to be able to identify themselves and there need to be trust relationships in effect. Before, a server would have an X.509 certificate to prove who or what it was, and now it needs a signed token. Requiring a service (and its human administrator) to go through an OAuth flow every time, say, a server restarts, is an intolerable burden on a system. Therefore, the trust is agreed upon separately with a service client. Typically, a service client has a single (robot) user and hence restricts which users can be recognized. The service then issues token requests directly.

RFC 7523

Public/private keys must be generated and all authentication is key-based. Once all is in place, the service simply issues a grant request (which is in JSON and also signed with the private key) to the token endpoint, signed with its keys, and gets tokens back. Read the RFC 7523 documentation for more

RFC 6749 ยง4.4

To authenticate, (as per ยง2.3 of the specification)

[t]he authorization server MAY accept any form of client authentication meeting its security requirements.

Hence you may use public/private keys with the client credentials flow too if your client has them. OA4MP will issue tokens based on the request. Read the client credentials flow documentation for more

The Token Information Endpoint

Token management is a necessity. OA4MP allows for an admin to query what tokens are currently in use by a user. This is done at the token endpoint by using a specific grant and the response includes all outstanding tokens of this user for every client that the admin administers.

The Request

An admin client makes a request to the authorization server's token endpoint using the extension grant type mechanism defined in Section 4.5 of RFC 6749.
Client authentication server is done using basic authorization. The request is made using either HTTP GET (preferred on philosophical grounds) or HTTP POST. The parameters are

grant_type (Required) must be urn:oa4mp:params:oauth:grant-type:token-info
access_token OR refresh_token (Required) and the value is resp. any (valid) access token or refresh token.

The Response

If the request is valid and meets all policy and other criteria of the authorization server, the successful token response has character set of "UTF-8", a media type of "application/json" and an HTTP 200 status code.

user_uid the unique id of the user
clients a JSON array of

The structure of the clients array is best described as follows.

    {"clients":[CLIENT+],
     "user_uid":USER_ID}

    CLIENT:
    {"client_id":CLIENT_ID,
     "transactions" : [TRANSACTION+]}

    TRANSACTION:
     {"code": AUTH_GRANT,
      "tokens":[{"access_token"|"refresh_token":TOKEN}+]

    TOKEN:
    {"is_valid":BOOLEAN,
    "lifetime":LONG,
    "issued_at":LONG,
    "jti":TOKEN_ID,
    "token":JWT
    }

     USER_UID: String
    CLIENT_ID: String
   AUTH_GRANT: String
     TOKEN_ID: String
          JWT: JSON Web Token

Response example

    HTTP/1.1 200 OK
    Content-Type: application/json
    Cache-Control: no-cache, no-store

    {
      "clients": [
        {
          "transactions": [
            {
              "code": "https://localhost:9443/oauth2/262005d0f72e0803828c0a098e87d1b1?type=authzGrant&ts=1654791488268&version=v2.0&lifetime=750000",
              "tokens": [
                {
                  "access_token": {
                    "is_valid": true,
                    "lifetime": 300000,
                    "issued_at": 1654791499644,
                    "jti": "https://localhost:9443/oauth2/468cfbff8cbe412393dd34d62ca2dc28?type=accessToken&ts=1654791499644&version=v2.0&lifetime=300000",
                    "token": "eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJraWQiOiIyOTc4RkY1NDhBNTVBNzM5NTAyRTNCQzY0QTU4RTJCMiIsImFsZyI6IlJTMjU2In0.eyJ3bGNnLnZlciI6IjEuMCIsImF1ZCI6Imh0dHBzOi8vbG9jYWxob3N0L2Zlcm1pbGFiIiwibXlfYXRfY2xhaW0iOiJteV9hdF9jbGFpbSIsIm5iZiI6MTY1NDc5MTQ4NywiaXNzIjoiaHR0cDovL2xvY2FsaG9zdDo5NDQzL2N1c3RvbS9pc3N1ZXIiLCJleHAiOjE2NTQ3OTE3OTIsImlhdCI6MTY1NDc5MTQ5MiwianRpIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9sb2NhbGhvc3Q6OTQ0My9vYXV0aDIvNDY4Y2ZiZmY4Y2JlNDEyMzkzZGQzNGQ2MmNhMmRjMjg_dHlwZT1hY2Nlc3NUb2tlbiZ0cz0xNjU0NzkxNDk5NjQ0JnZlcnNpb249djIuMCZsaWZldGltZT0zMDAwMDAiLCJzY29wZSI6InJlYWQ6L2hvbWUvaHR0cDovL2NpbG9nb24ub3JnL3NlcnZlclQvdXNlcnMvMjEzNDAzNjMgd3JpdGU6L2RhdGEvaHR0cDovL2NpbG9nb24ub3JnL3NlcnZlclQvdXNlcnMvMjEzNDAzNjMvY2x1c3RlciB4Lnk6L2FiYy9kZWYiLCJzdWIiOiJodHRwOi8vY2lsb2dvbi5vcmcvc2VydmVyVC91c2Vycy8yMTM0MDM2MyJ9.j9wK9EkNy19oKNKPqP0uGxuFB7il4Ddoq2gWlrt1Mk_oISDMOnVnzGn35HjGP2XuNDIjrVIRE3D5JyylEw_CL19_sXlNqEmNnyCq4Um4fuGZ5d0evpA0n_G2v8U59fEZf98I1WJ0KsMB2L5SJOXJzMce9Pvt5DC56He8GruFt3IkSEq6d1J1kwCGymyul_izmXUlQ5XMs2r5EeinERElkmPaB2jsj56H5TLrbet_7Z8nk5Ds3DGT59OtfhRGc_HRaRGG6x2J0imHgn4JvyPPgR80nX3yoGmmw5gU3HvEbrqG39XjFzSwnWqQv-XiaRZspjzy5Ns7_-v5oeczXZYAsA"
                  },
                  "refresh_token": {
                    "is_valid": true,
                    "lifetime": 900000,
                    "issued_at": 1654791499644,
                    "jti": "https://localhost:9443/oauth2/5040b30aaa66b0889284738917de4ae?type=refreshToken&ts=1654791499644&version=v2.0&lifetime=900000",
                    "token": "eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJub25lIn0.eyJhdWQiOiJodHRwczovL2xvY2FsaG9zdC90ZXN0IiwibmJmIjoxNjU0NzkxNDg3LCJteV9ydF9jbGFpbSI6Im15X3J0X2NsYWltIiwiZXhwIjoxNjU0NzkyMzkyLCJpYXQiOjE2NTQ3OTE0OTIsImp0aSI6Imh0dHBzOi8vbG9jYWxob3N0Ojk0NDMvb2F1dGgyLzUwNDBiMzBhYWE2NmIwODg5Mjg0NzM4OTE3ZGU0YWU_dHlwZT1yZWZyZXNoVG9rZW4mdHM9MTY1NDc5MTQ5OTY0NCZ2ZXJzaW9uPXYyLjAmbGlmZXRpbWU9OTAwMDAwIn0."
                  }
                }
              ]
            },
    "user_uid": "http://cilogon.org/serverT/users/21340363"
    }

Caveat

If the user has been extremely active and has a lot of tokens, this may be a truly massive listing. It is best assume that and pipe it someplace safe. It is also possible to get missing tokens. This means that the user started a flow and either has abandoned it, or not come back yet to finish it.

Listing other clients

Admin clients may be allowed to list the user in other clients, meaning, if they have been granted the privilege, this call will return every token for this user regardless of which clients the user has used. Default is to restrict tokens to those clients that the admin owns.

Introduction

The authentication module for OA4MP can be replaced by various means, such as using Tomcat's built in management, or even a complete standalone replacement. However, this means that you will need to have separate logins that you manage for each user. Another option is using a proxy service. This is an OIDC service that allows for logins. Your OA4MP can simply forward all requested scopes to that service (including the device flow) and use the service, allowing your users to effectively log in there. In short, it allows some other service to do all your user management, since you establish a trust relation that logins on the proxy are exactly the logins on your system..

How does this do it?

You need to register a client with the proxy service (henceforth known as the proxy), then enable using proxies in your server configuration (see below). Since the service is a client of the proxy, you need to enable the callback servlet and register that as the callback. There is nothign special about this client, it is a standard OAuth or OIDC client.

Configuring the server

The Tomcat deployment descriptor (web.xml)

There is an included web.xml file, at $OA4MP_SERVER/etc/WEB-INF/proxy-web.xml that has a complete setup. Copy that over your web.xml file, then restart Tomcat. The major point is that it enables the callback servlet (with endpoint ready) at

/oauth2/ready

and when you are registering your client with the proxy, you need to set this callback to

https://host:port/oauth2/ready

in a standard install. Key points are that https should be available, and that your server should be at host:port. The proxy must be able to contact your callback endpoint securely, so self-signed certs should be avoided unless you have a specific agreement with the proxy.

The server configuration proper

You need to have using the proxy enabled within the authorizationServlet tag and set the configuration file as well as the name of the configuration for the client. Remember that this file is the configuration for a complete OAuth 2 client. If you need to, read up on the client configuration file syntax. A very typical entry in the server configuration file would be

    <authorizationServlet useProxy="true"
                          cfgFile="/opt/oa4mp/etc/client.xml"
                          cfgName="cilogon-proxy"
                        />

Configuring the client

The server configuration attribute cfgFile points to a standard OA4MP client configuration. This may be in its own configuration file or in the main server configuration, e.g.

<config> <service> ... server config </service> <client> .. client config </client> </config>

Using the Proxy

When your service contacts the proxy, a complete exchange is done including getting any claims from the proxy. This means that these are available for your service to harvest. The system will always set the subject to the subject returned by the proxy. You may configure a list of other claims from the proxy to be returned. This is done in the proxy_claims_list property of the client. The options there are

* = (an asterisk) pass along all claims, the default
[claim0,claim1,...] = list of specific claims. Note that putting * in this list will simply return all claims.except audience, issuer, issued at, expiration because these must come from the current server, not the proxy (or any consumer of the id token must reject it.)

So if the proxy returns the following claims

    {"sub":"user_123",
     "idp":"https:shibboleth.big_state.edu",
     "is_member_of":["admin","all-users","admin-phys"]
    }

Then at the least the server returns the "sub" claim. If you set the client's proxy_claims_list to do so, you may also return the idp or is_member_of claim. If you set the proxy_claims_list to be "*" then all relevant the claims will be passed along.

Configuring the scopes your client is to use with the proxy

Using the scopes in the client configuration

Each client may be configured to request specific scopes from the proxy. These are in the attribute proxy_request_scopes. An empty list means to request no scopes. In that case, the proxy simply confirms that the user has a valid login on that system. A list that contains an asterisk ("*") means to request all scopes in the client's configuration file. If there is an asterisk anywhere on the list, all are requested.

Forwarding the scopes from the request.

It is also possible that the client should simply forward scopes from the user request. In that case, set the attribute forward_scopes_to_proxy to true. (Since the user may be requesting scopes for refresh and access tokens as well, this implies the proxy service is able to resolve these, so it is also performing authorization for the user.) If this flag is true, then the of scopes in the configuration you have will be ignored.

Note that forwarding has precedence, so setting this flag true will override sending scopes in proxy_request_scopes.